Guide to the Women's Athletics at Stanford Collection SC0496
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Women's athletics at Stanford collection
1971-1995
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Shuer, Marjorie.
SC0496
1 Linear Feet
These papers were largely collected by Marjorie Shuer and include video tapes, audio tapes, and research notes from an oral history project; and miscellaneous correspondence, questionnaires, clippings, and memorabilia. The video tapes are interviews with Joseph H. Ruetz, Athletic Director at Stanford University from 1972 to 1978, and with Rosamond Clarke Bacon and Paula Burr, both members of the class of 1930 and active in student athletics; the audio tapes include interviews with Richard Lyman, Stanford University President during the 1970s, Shirley Schoof, Sherri Posthumous, Barbara Gelpi, Myra Strober, Jing Lyman, and Iris Litt. The research notes were compiled by Jennifer Dalton, Laura Hayward, and Renee Pavelski. Subjects include the strengthening and developing of women's athletics during and after the merger of the athletic and physical education departments (1972); and student and athletic experiences of the 1930s, including the Women's Athletic Association. Both Bacon and Burr discuss taking courses with Dr. Clelia Mosher. Bacon also talks about her house on campus and the removal of faculty housing during the construction of the Law School. Other items include letters to Jon Denney, 1995, from Stanford female athletes active prior to the passage of Title IX; letters to Marjorie Shuer, 1986 and 1993; two questionnaires on Stanford sports; programs from the Block S Awards honoring women athletes at Stanford, 1995; and class papers by Jennifer Dalton, Laura Hayward, and Renee Pavelski, 1995.
Information about Access
Student papers may not be photocopied.
Description of the Collection
These papers were largely collected by Marjorie Shuer and include video tapes, audio tapes, and research notes from an oral history project; and miscellaneous correspondence, questionnaires, clippings, and memorabilia. The video tapes are interviews with Joseph H. Ruetz, Athletic Director at Stanford University from 1972 to 1978, and with Rosamond Clarke Bacon and Paula Burr, both members of the class of 1930 and active in student athletics; the audio tapes include interviews with Richard Lyman, Stanford University President during the 1970s, Shirley Schoof, Sherri Posthumous, Barbara Gelpi, Myra Strober, Jing Lyman, and Iris Litt. The research notes were compiled by Jennifer Dalton, Laura Hayward, and Renee Pavelski. Subjects include the strengthening and developing of women's athletics during and after the merger of the athletic and physical education departments (1972); and student and athletic experiences of the 1930s, including the Women's Athletic Association. Both Bacon and Burr discuss taking courses with Dr. Clelia Mosher. Bacon also talks about her house on campus and the removal of faculty housing during the construction of the Law School. Other items include letters to Jon Denney, 1995, from Stanford female athletes active prior to the passage of Title IX; letters to Marjorie Shuer, 1986 and 1993; two questionnaires on Stanford sports; programs from the Block S Awards honoring women athletes at Stanford, 1995; and class papers by Jennifer Dalton, Laura Hayward, and Renee Pavelski, 1995.
Phonotapes.; Oral histories.; Sports for women.; Videorecordings.; Athletics; Ruetz, Joseph H.; Stanford University. Department of Athletics; Shuer, Marjorie.; Lyman, Richard W.; Bacon, Rosamond Clarke.; Stanford University. Women's Athletic Association; Mosher, Clelia Duel; Stanford University. Department of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation; Burr, Paula Weinstein.
- Records
  - "Mr. Ruetz Stanford Athletic Director 1972-79, [re] AIAW, NCAA, SAB, Buck and Cardinal Club, Preparation for merger of Athletic and PE Dept.", 1995 Apr 23; 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - Rosamund Clarke Bacon '30 Pres. WAA BB, FH Track and Paula Weinstein Burr '30, took course from Dr. Clelia D. Mosher", 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 1)
  - Block S Awards Ceremony, 1995 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1971-75 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Intramural handbook, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter re Title IX from Christopher M. Horpel to Congressman McKeon, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Jon Denny from former Stanford women athletes, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Margie Shuer from Pam Strathairn; and Fred Glover, 1986, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letterhead of Organization of Stanford Women Athletes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Questionnaire results on freshmen participation in varsity athletics (by Undergraduate Studies Office), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Questionnaire and results done by Terrie McDonald as background for a Stanford Daily article, 1974 May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Research notes, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Soccer team, correspondence of players re coach B. Andeberhan, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Partial transcript of video interview with Rosamund Bacon (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Statements by Stanford University students: statement for news conference on media's perception of women at Stanford; and "Warriors of Justice," by Stanford sophomore on her high school sports experience, 1974 Feb 22; 1994 Oct (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interviews (Box 2)
    - Clarke Bacon, Rosamund and Paula Weinstein Burr, 1994
    - Cohen, Elizabeth, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    - Degler, Carl, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    - Dornbusch, Sanford M. (Box 2)
    - Gelpi, Barbara, 1994; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    - Litt, Iris, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    - Lougee, Carolyn, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    - Lyman, Jing, 1992 and 1994; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    - Lyman, Richard W., 1995; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    - Posthumous, Sherri, 1995; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    - Schoof, Shirley, 1995-05-11
    - Strober, Myra, 1994; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    - Tyack, David, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
  - Dalton, Jennifer, “Stanford Women’s Athletics: 1970-1995” (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hayward, Laura, “Women’s Athletics at Stanford University: A Historical Perspective (1938-1970)”, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pavelski, Renee, “History of Stanford Women’s Athletics (1891-1939)”, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Telegram (copy) re presenting paper at Athletic Conference of American College Women at Berkeley, 1924 Mar 7 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Timeline of SU athletic directors (Box 3, Folder 5)